<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-07T10:05:05-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blog</title><subtitle>A blog about inventing the laws of nature.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">math.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/MATH.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="math." /><published>2019-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/MATH</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/05/MATH.html">&lt;p&gt;I like to think of physics as &lt;em&gt;looking at reality&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;saying what happens&lt;/em&gt;. In this sense, there is no such thing as something ‘breaking the laws of physics’. If it happens, it’s real; if it’s real, it’s physics. If something &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like it breaks the laws of physics, either&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a) You’ve been tricked somehow and that’s not what actually happened, or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;b) You got the laws of physics wrong, and the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; laws are actually different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If it happens, it’s real; if it’s real, it’s physics&lt;/em&gt;. So a chicken flapping its wings, or someone dropping their cell phone in jello, or a bathtub filled with ants - those are all physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t sound terribly useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real trick of physics is to try to say as much as possible in as few words as possible. Right away then, our descriptions above run into limitations: “chickens flap their wings” only works for chickens, not for wolves or badgers. “Someone drops their cell phone in jello” is not a very common event, and you can’t easily predict when it will happen - maybe if you knew someone very clumsy and you surrounded them with jello while they were holding their phone. The same thing goes for a bathtub full of ants: it’s a one-time event, something very unlikely to occur, and even if it did you’d have a hard time predicting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; when people do physics, they talk about things that they can predict, events that happen a lot. That way you can describe many events at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another problem with the descriptions above: they only work if someone knows what the words mean. If you know what a chicken is, what wings are, and what flapping is, then that description makes sense to you. But what if you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; know what a chicken is? Then I have to describe it, and that takes up more words. If you know about birds, then maybe I can describe a chicken as a type of bird. What happens if you don’t know about cell phones, or jello? Those things are much harder to describe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then really our goal is this: describe as much as possible, in as few words as possible, to as many people as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an example: I could say, “if you hold a rock in your hand above the ground and let it go, it will end up on the ground.” This is a fairly general statement: it applies to all rocks, and it applies to anyone who can let go of a rock. However, we can do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Objects move towards the ground, so long as nothing gets in the way.” This is pretty good. Now it applies to more than just rocks, and it doesn’t matter if a person is there or not. You can probably think up some exceptions to the rule, but it works in &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; cases. Yet we can be even more descriptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Objects accelerate straight towards the ground at 9.8 meters per second squared”. This is a very specific description indeed! As before there are exceptions - for example, the acceleration of a sheet of paper is less than 9.8 meters per second squared. Still, the rule works for a lot of things. Moreover, it tells me &lt;em&gt;exactly how fast&lt;/em&gt; something moves towards the ground, instead of just saying “it falls.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rule has come at a cost: I have used some new words here. We need to define “accelerate”, “meter”, and “second”. Meter and second are not so bad. If I have a stick that is a meter long, I can point to it and say “this much”. Similarly, I can clap my hands in a steady rhythm to demonstrate how long a second is.  Accelerate is a bit more difficult, but is doable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, there is something much harder to describe in this sentence: “9.8”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you describe &lt;em&gt;numbers&lt;/em&gt; to someone who doesn’t know what a number is? Or in other words: how do we invent &lt;em&gt;mathematics&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language of physics is math. It is the tool that you use to describe the most amount possible. In a sense, that is what math was &lt;em&gt;created&lt;/em&gt; for: to describe specific types of patterns in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math is not limited to describing physics, however. Physics is constrained by what is real; if something &lt;em&gt;cannot happen&lt;/em&gt;, it is not physics. There is no physics for one apple and one apple making zero apples. On the other hand, you can create mathematics where 1+1=0 (&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite_field&quot;&gt;yes, really!&lt;/a&gt;) You can make up whatever rules you like - the only rule in math is &lt;em&gt;no contradictions&lt;/em&gt;. So if you use your rules to show that something is true, and then use the &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt; rules to show that something is false, you’ve done the math wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics is all that exists. Mathematics is &lt;em&gt;anything you can think of that isn’t contradictory&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequence of this is that math is more abstract than physics. If physics is about “the patterns of nature”, then mathematics might be called “the patterns of patterns”. Historically, this has lead to mathematics being more rigorous than physics. If you want to know who’s right and who’s wrong about a physics question, you can build a device or run an experiment to test your idea. You can always &lt;em&gt;point at reality&lt;/em&gt;. In mathematics, there’s nothing to point to, and so it’s much harder to tell the difference between being right and just making something up. Thus, a mathematician’s reasoning must be totally airtight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to do physics, you must be prepared to do math. But &lt;em&gt;inventing&lt;/em&gt; the math - seeing how it works at the same deep level that we want for the physics - is extremely difficult. What is a line? What is counting? These things are intuitive and easy to overlook because we were taught them as children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point I want to make is that inventing physics is hard enough; inventing the &lt;em&gt;language&lt;/em&gt; to talk about physics is beyond my current abilities. So I won’t be able to describe &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; for you. I will have to trust that you know what 9.8 means, and that you understand what squaring a number is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let us dicuss our first physical concept.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>r.m.</name></author><summary type="html">The language of physics is math.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">abstraction.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/03/ABSTRACTION.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="abstraction." /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/03/ABSTRACTION</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/03/ABSTRACTION.html">&lt;p&gt;At the dawn of intelligence, there is no language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no words to describe sensations; only sensations. There are experiences and stories, but no storytellers yet. How do they come about? Where does the concept of a concept come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of “ideas” begins with language, and to develop a language you might start by recognizing objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do you go about recognizing objects?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are walking along at night. Turning a corner, you see in the distance a figure. It’s far away and in the low light hard to distinguish; is it a person, or merely a tree?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human perception has a limited resolution, so even though a person is not the same as a tree, they might &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; the same under certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you step closer, they become easier to distinguish. Trees are often taller than people; trees usually have a blob of green at the top; people usually have four limbs and trees have many; people tend to move more than trees do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an important lesson to be learned here: &lt;em&gt;objects are distinguished by their properties&lt;/em&gt;. In liquistic terms you might say it another way: &lt;em&gt;nouns are distinguished by their adjectives&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nouns are things that you can point to, or hold in your hand, like a cup or a rock. If someone asks what an apple is, you can pick one up and show them as an example. Adjectives are trickier. You will not find a “big” roaming in the wild. There are big people, and big trees, and big apples; but there is no such thing as a “big” all by itself. The same holds for many other adjectives: there are green things, but no green; you can have five rocks or five sticks or five melons, but you cannot grasp a five with your fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet adjectives are how we recognize nouns in the first place. A tree is green, and people are not green; that is one way to tell them apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does the label “tree” exist in the first place? Because there is a set of objects that have similar characteristics, so we lump them together under the term “tree”. The key is not just noticing when objects have something in common; it’s noticing when objects &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; have something in common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No two trees are exactly alike, just as no two shades of green are exactly alike. But if the color of two things is close - similar enough that you might mistake one for the other at a distance, in low light, with clumsy, low-res human senses - then you can apply the same label to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not just how language is built, but many other skills as well. A drawing of a tree is not the same thing as a tree; but by recognizing the shapes that are common to trees in general, you can create an image that &lt;em&gt;looks like&lt;/em&gt; a tree, even if it isn’t exactly the same as one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this ability - &lt;em&gt;recognizing shapes that things have in common&lt;/em&gt; - this is the power that mathematics runs on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>r.m.</name></author><summary type="html">The idea of &quot;ideas&quot; begins with language.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">physics.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/01/PHYSICS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="physics." /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/01/PHYSICS</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/01/PHYSICS.html">&lt;p&gt;Stephen Hawking asked, in his Brief History of Time, “What do we know about the universe, and how do we know it?”  I’d like to probe the meaning of this question further with three anecdotes from my time as a physics TA, connected by a theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lightbulbs&quot;&gt;The Lightbulbs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a standard question given to students in an introductory course in electricity and magnetism:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Two lightbulbs &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; are connected in series to a battery. Which lightbulb is brighter, or are they equal in brightness?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students at this stage haven’t been told what the answer is; they are meant to figure it out. The teacher has taught them what it means for two things to be connected in series; they know Ohm’s law; and they are presumably familiar with lightbulbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to imagine that those are the only facts about this situation you know: how would you come to the answer? What would you write on your page?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had given this question many times before, and in spring of 2016 I gave it again. As I went around the class asking students to share their reasoning, I came across a group who said something like this: “We’ve decided that A is brigher than B. Now we’re trying to come up with a reason for &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; A is brighter than B.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;e-pur-si-muove&quot;&gt;“E pur si muove”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a lecture I would give to students in an Astronomy class I taught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, dance and waggle your arms around all weird, and ask, “Am I moving?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The response to this (amid some laughter) is usually yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next step: ask, “How do you know I am moving?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students can easily overthink this one, but the simple answer is sufficient: they use their eyes and can see when things are moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Okay, so what if you were blind? Could you still tell if I were moving?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure. You can usually hear when something is moving, and if not, you can feel it moving - either by the breeze as it passes by, or by stickin’ your fingers on whatever’s moving and feel it move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then: “Based on these things only, does the Earth move?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it is surprising that some people will &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; say &lt;em&gt;yes&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you ask a &lt;em&gt;final&lt;/em&gt; question: “If the Earth is moving, how do you know? Can you see it moving with your eyes? Can you hear it moving from the sound it makes? Can you feel it moving with your body?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then why do you think it’s moving?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;electrons&quot;&gt;Electrons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in 2018, I was talking with a fellow student about how physics is taught. In particular, I mentioned how professors rarely &lt;em&gt;demonstrated&lt;/em&gt; the laws of physics to you - normally, they just tell you equations and make you do math. No one had ever &lt;em&gt;shown&lt;/em&gt; me that electrons exist, for example, and I was frustrated because I wanted to see these things with my own eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The student responded that such a philosophy doesn’t always work in practice. For example, there’s no way to see the electron - it’s too tiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was once a time when the laws of physics were not known. At some point, no one knew if you could make one lightbulb shine brighter than another by swapping their order in a circuit. At some point, no one considered the possibility that the Earth moves. And of course, we have not always known that electrons exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So perhaps a better question is this: if you &lt;em&gt;really didn’t know&lt;/em&gt; what the answer to a question was, how would you find out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the answer is easy. Will the first or second lightbulb shine brighter in a series circuit? You can get two lightbulbs, some wire, and a battery, and try it out yourself. But sometimes the answer is harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the Earth move? Well, I don’t see it moving, or hear it, or feel it, so why would I think it moves in the first place? Because somebody important told me “The Earth moves”, and I was gullible enough to believe them? Well, who told them? And in the very beginning, what made somebody think the Earth moved in the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do electrons exist? How do you know? We’re told that electrons are tiny dots, smaller than what you can see with just your eyes. In fact, they are so small that a normal microscope with a glass lens wouldn’t be able to see it, no matter how powerful it was. So what did the first person to discover an electron see, then? They couldn’t use their eyes, or a microscope. What made them say, “This is a new thing; it is not a coin, or a chair, or a tree, or a cat; it is something different, and I am going to call it an electron.” How did they find it? And how did they prove it to other people, how did they &lt;em&gt;show&lt;/em&gt; them that electrons exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science is hard.  Really, really hard.  The stuff we take for granted is especially hard, and once you realize that, you start to notice that it’s some kind of goddamned miracle that anybody figured it out in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes it science is the ability to &lt;em&gt;predict patterns&lt;/em&gt; and, if only in principle, that anyone could verify that those patterns are correct. The ability to check for yourself is essential: you cannot determine what is true by deciding what you want the answer to be, then coming up with clever reasons for why it must be so. No matter how convincing your words sound, electrons still exist, the Earth still moves, and two lightbulbs connected in series will shine with the same brigtness. Nor is it wise to just repeat the words that someone else says; just because someone says it does not make it true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, my primary goal is for you to &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; where the laws of physics came from: what you would do to &lt;em&gt;demonstrate&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;discover&lt;/em&gt; them. This is not an easy task! But we have an advantage. As Newton said: “If I have seen further, it is by standing on the shoulders of giants.” We are not trying to discover new laws; we only hope to find out how the existing laws were &lt;em&gt;originally&lt;/em&gt; discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, following the ancients is not infallible! The first scientists did not always take the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; path; they didn’t know what questions to ask, and were blinded by bias and emotional ties to incorrect answers.  They often explored paths that led nowhere but dead-ends, or paths that &lt;em&gt;seemed&lt;/em&gt; like the right answer until someone cleverer came along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not particularly interested in revisiting all the mistakes made in the past.  Occasionally I will throw in a historical tidbit, because it’s interesting.  That said, I see no reason to spend 2000 years believing the Earth is at the center of the universe, or that the stars are made of aether. Or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I wish to cut across the garbage and make use of the most efficient route to truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My starting point for this journey is to show you the basic laws of &lt;em&gt;mechanics&lt;/em&gt;, or the rules of how things move. And, as stated, I want to avoid just &lt;em&gt;telling&lt;/em&gt; you what the pattern is. Rather, I will show you how to see the pattern yourself, with your own two eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get this effect, I’m going to imagine someone living back at the beginning, before the laws were created. This won’t be a true historical account - our idealized scientist will always have a knack for asking the right questions and using the correct tools; they have the time and resources to build a testing apparatus for every experiment they like.  What they lack is the knowledge - you can’t just say to them “The Earth moves!”  They simply won’t believe you.  You have to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I will avoid using modern technology as much as possible. It is true that you can demonstrate the laws of gravity much more easily using your phone’s stopwatch and camera. But do you know how the stopwatch and camera work? It takes away from your understanding when all of the complicated machinery is hidden inside a magic rectangle. If your phone says something took 0.4 seconds to happen, how do you know that’s the truth? Is it any better than just believing facts that someone else tells you? I argue that it is not, and that we can do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these things in mind, let’s begin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>r.m.</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;What do we know about the universe, and how do we know it?&quot;</summary></entry></feed>